The Middle Ages got its name because it is seen as a middle period.
The dull transport route between times that really matters.
A time of darkness and decay when people died like flies.
A thousand years of boring, but is that true?
Yes partially.
There are plague epidemics, migrations, war and persecution-
-But also a flowering time for e.g.
agriculture.
Positive things also happen.
Everything is not black or white, and a thousand years are not a parenthes-
-So what happened during the Middle Ages, and what was it like to live then?
Europe's early history can be divided into three eras.
Many people move out into the countryside and become self -sufficient.
There is still a solid foundation to lean on - and have around your neck.
Here I have a cross, and it shows that we are Christians during the Middle Ages.
The church governs the entire life of man, from the cradle to the grave.
Religion is always present, and one should be reminded of it.
The church remains as a unifying kitt-
-For a politically divided Europe that is still connected culturally.
The church makes sure to preserve the Latin language-
-And the organization of the church extends over several kingdoms.
But a period of cold and humid climate leads to malnourish and starvation
-and that's not even the worst.
They suffer from a bulge.
The first proper pandemic.
The Justinian plague harvests 25 million lives.
The church is given a very great meaning-
-For the church can explain all the evil.
Why is it starvation and illness?
Religion was nothing that just took place in the head or heart.
It was part of society.
They thought about society as a Christian.
Church is the only strong organization-
-And becomes one of the strongest powers in Europe.
For the weak kings, the church becomes crucial to regain power.
One who allies with the church is Karl the Great.
-When a way to administer the kingdom.
Karl's solution leads to a whole new social system: the feudal community.
But how does it work?
The king, as the church proclaimed king of God's grace, governs over an area-
-But he lacks money and soldiers, so he splits his land.
The areas are granted - they are given to great men who swear a loss of allegiance.
They also have to pay with surplus from agriculture and assist with soldiers.
Those who work on agriculture are farmers who do not own their land.
The feudal community is often illustrated with a pyramid, but that is to simplify.
A woman loudly up-
-Can have more in common with a peasant woman than her husband.
There are village teams and Gillen.
Organizations that are not hierarchical.
Everyone has a place and sees themselves as part of a unit.
In Sweden, we are far from this.
While the rest of Europe has the Middle Ages, we are still in the Viking Age.
On Europe's coasts, the Viking ship spreads fear.
You plunder, promise protection and shop.
In this way, the Vikings are an expression of a community form-
-Or serves as sea -borne kingdoms, with control of different land areas.
The Vikings are dependent on water-
-And much of their success lies in their ship technology.
Man draws up a method of producing very thin table plank-
-So that it becomes light, basic ship.
You have sails that have taken years to produce.
In the 11th century Sweden enters the Middle Ages-
-When we follow the rest of Europe and embrace Christianity.
The king Olof Skötkonung is baptizing, and the old Asa gods are phased out.
But how much does life change?
The big change is that one does not burise at home at the yard-
The crusade idea is that it is a defense war.
You want to defend Christianity and take back Christian areas.
After the loss of the Holy Land, the Church must bring people-
-In the struggle to take it back from the Muslims.
The crusades are a war against the enemies of the church-
-Which gives forgiveness for your sins.
But for Christians it is a sin to kill someone.
Why can people suddenly imagine breaking one of the commandments?
The main explanation is mental.
They tried desperately to remove a shame.
Everyone sins in some way.
Had one killed their mother-in-law, which happened-
—kind the Grandma who made it-
-In seven years go around to the churches in the diocese and ask for forgiveness.
They didn't like it, but you could get bred and replace the confession-
-mot that e.g.
danger on crusades, and it was much more fun.
For a hundred years, crusades go in Europe-
This barrel was at home with someone.
In this casserole, which you just see the paw, have someone cooked.
We are Catholics and fasting.
Then you ate fish, a little more fish and maybe even more fish.
Then we must define “fish”-
-And, according to the Middle Ages, it was an animal in the water.
Therefore, you could eat beaver and seals.
In order to sell fish, the merchant must into the city-
-As has a lot of different rules.
You organize and decide who is allowed to perform crafts and shop.
There is no free market economy.
Despite rules, life is now at its best on the Middle Ages-
-With flourishing city life, beaver in the stomach and existing trade.
But don't shout hello until you're over the creek.
As the population increases, there is competition for work and land.
Many may grow where there are no good harvests.
In some places it is malnutrition, and the population decreases.
And then comes the killing: the death of the poet.
1347 is the plague back.
Venice is first affected by the disease, and no one is left untouched.
Listen to this contemporary poem by Italian Francesco Petrarca.
No cheerful noises.
People wonder why they suffer from horrors.
The obvious explanation is-
-That the God who rule over the universe is twisted on the people.
Some who get better are the farmers who survive.
The fields are empty and have never been so cheap.
Farmers can buy their own land and break away from their feudal lord.
Others also break away from the feudal system: the kings.
To raise money, they dust off the old Roman tax system.
With the tax system, the king can tax more.
It creates an improved administration and richer royal power
-As can increase their power over the people and expand over other kingdoms.
With that, the feudal community begins to loosen up.
About then Columbus gets out on the open sea-
-And it is seen as the end of the Middle Ages.
In the Arabian Peninsula, Islam brings a huge development of knowledge-
-In medicine, astronomy and mathematics.
How, then, can we know all this?
It's a bit like a puzzle.
You have to have many pieces in place.
There are raged house walls, fireplaces and clothes that people have had.
When you pull up posts in long houses they can smell tar-
-For they have impregnated them for them to last longer.
However, we do not need to pull up posts to find traces of the Middle Ages.
It is a basic period for the most part in our society.
City life - the urban - is a medieval invention.
As we walk in an old town, along crooked, winding streets-
-To we walk in the footsteps of our medieval predecessors.
Swedish texture: Per Lundgren Iyuno-Di Group for UR